<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wayfire_shell_unstable_v2">
  <interface name="zwf_shell_manager_v2" version="3">
    <description summary="DE integration">
      This protocol provides additional events and requests for special DE
      clients like panels, docks, etc.

      It is meant as an addition for protocols like wlr-layer-shell.
    </description>

    <request name="get_wf_output">
      <description summary="Create a zwf_output_v2 for the given wl_output"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwf_output_v2"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_wf_surface">
      <description summary="Create a zwf_surface_v2 for the given wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwf_surface_v2"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwf_output_v2" version="3">
    <description summary="A wrapper for wl_output">
      Represents a single output.
      Each output is managed independently from the others.
    </description>

    <event name="enter_fullscreen">
      <description summary="A window was fullscreened">
        Emitted when a window gets fullscreened on the given output. In this
        mode, windows in the TOP layer are not visible.

        There will be no two consecutive enter_fullscreen calls, i.e. if
        fullscreen mode is entered it will be exited before going into this mode
        again.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="leave_fullscreen">
      <description summary="A window was fullscreened">
        Emitted when the output is no longer in fullscreen mode. Each
        leave_fullscreen has a corresponding enter_fullscreen before it.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="inhibit_output">
      <description summary="Don't render the output">
        Request the compositor to not render the output, so the output usually
        is cleared to black color.  To enable output rendering again, call
        inhibit_output_done.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="inhibit_output_done">
      <description summary="Render the output">
        Stop inhibiting the output. This must be called as many times as
        inhibit_output was called to actually uninhibit rendering.

        The inhibit/inhibit_done requests can be called multiple times, even
        from different apps, so don't assume that a call to inhibit_done would
        always mean actually starting the rendering process.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="hotspot_edge">
      <entry name="top" value="1" summary="Top edge of the output"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="2" summary="Bottom edge of the output"/>
      <entry name="left" value="4" summary="Left edge of the output"/>
      <entry name="right" value="8" summary="Right edge of the output"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="create_hotspot">
      <description summary="Create a hotspot on the output edge or corner">
        A hotspot on the output is an edge or a corner region of the
        output where the mouse or touch point has been residing for a given
        amount of time.

        The hotspot can be used for example for autohiding panels, where the
        panel is shown when the input hovers on the edge of the output for a
        specific amount of time.

        For edge hotspots (single edge), the entire edge region of 'threshold'
        pixels depth triggers the hotspot.

        For corner hotspots (two adjacent edges), the corner region of
        'threshold' pixels by 'threshold' pixels triggers the hotspot.
      </description>

      <arg name="hotspot" type="uint" summary="bitwise or of the edges (1-2 edges)"/>
      <arg name="threshold" type="uint" summary="distance from the edge or corner of the output in pixels"/>
      <arg name="timeout" type="uint" summary="minimum time for input to be in the hotspot (ms)"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwf_hotspot_v2"/>
    </request>

    <!-- Version 2 additions -->
    <event name="toggle_menu" since="2">
      <description summary="Toggle menu event">
        Tells the menu to toggle open or close.

        Emitted using an activator binding.
      </description>
    </event>

    <!-- Version 3 additions -->
    <request name="create_custom_hotspot" since="3">
      <description summary="Create an arbitrary rectangular hotspot">
        Creates a hotspot for an arbitrary axis-aligned rectangle on the output.
        The rectangle is defined in output-local coordinates with (x, y) as the
        top-left corner, and (w, h) as width and height.

        The hotspot activates when the input pointer comes within 'threshold'
        pixels of any point on the rectangle's boundary. The proximity event
        reports the exact distance (0 to threshold) from the pointer to the
        nearest point on the rectangle boundary.

        This is a generalization of edge and corner hotspots:
        - A top edge hotspot is a rectangle covering the entire top edge
          with w = output.width, h = threshold, positioned at (0, 0)
        - A corner hotspot is a square of size threshold x threshold
          positioned at the output corner

        Use cases include:
        - Trigger zones that aren't aligned to output edges
        - Complex panel layouts where activation regions are around specific UI elements
        - Desktop widgets that expand/collapse based on pointer approach

        Note: The rectangle should be within the output bounds. The compositor
        may clamp it to output geometry or ignore rectangles entirely outside.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="uint" summary="X position of rectangle (output-local)"/>
      <arg name="y" type="uint" summary="Y position of rectangle (output-local)"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="Width of rectangle in pixels"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="Height of rectangle in pixels"/>
      <arg name="threshold" type="uint" summary="Distance from rectangle boundary that triggers hotspot"/>
      <arg name="timeout" type="uint" summary="Timeout in milliseconds"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwf_hotspot_v2"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwf_hotspot_v2" version="3">
    <description summary="A hotspot region on an output">
      Represents a region on an output that triggers when the input pointer
      remains within it for a specified timeout period.

      Hotspots can be either edge-based (full edge or corner) or positioned
      (a specific point on an edge).

      The lifecycle of a hotspot interaction is:
      1. Pointer enters hotspot area -> timeout timer starts
      2. After timeout, enter event is sent
      3. While pointer remains inside hotspot area, proximity_changed events
         are sent as the pointer moves
      4. Pointer leaves hotspot area -> leave event is sent
    </description>

    <event name="enter">
      <description summary="Hotspot was activated after timeout">
        Means that the mouse and/or touch finger was inside the indicated
        hotspot for the given amount of timeout time.

        After receiving this event, the client can expect proximity_changed
        events as the pointer moves within the hotspot, and eventually a
        leave event when the pointer exits.

        Emitted at most once for each entry of the input inside the hotspot.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="leave">
      <description summary="Input left hotspot">
        This event indicates that the mouse or touch point has left the hotspot
        area.

        After this event, no further proximity_changed events will be sent
        until a new enter event.

        Emitted only once after each enter.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="proximity_changed" since="3">
      <description summary="Proximity to trigger point changed">
        Sent after an enter event and before the corresponding leave event,
        whenever the input pointer moves within the hotspot area.

        Proximity is defined as the Euclidean distance in pixels from the input
        pointer to the hotspot's trigger geometry, clamped to the threshold:
        - 0: Input pointer is exactly at the trigger point
        - threshold: Input pointer is at the outer edge of the hotspot radius
          (just entered the hotspot area)
        - Values in between: Linear distance from trigger point

        This allows clients to implement pixel-perfect smooth feedback without
        needing to know the threshold value used to create the hotspot.

        For standard edge/corner hotspots (created via create_hotspot), the
        "threshold" is the distance from the edge parameter. The trigger point
        is defined as the closest point on the edge to the input pointer.

        For positioned hotspots (created via create_positioned_hotspot), the
        threshold is the radius parameter, and the trigger point is the exact
        point on the edge specified by position.

        The compositor should send this event at the same frequency as pointer
        motion events to ensure smooth animations.
      </description>

      <arg name="proximity" type="uint" summary="Shortest distance in pixels to trigger geometry (0 = at trigger, threshold = at edge)"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwf_surface_v2" version="3">
    <description summary="A special surface"/>
    <request name="interactive_move">
      <description summary="Start an interactive move of the surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

</protocol>
